Register of the Laissez Faire Books records
Hoover Institution Archives
Laissez Faire Books records
1957-2008
2007C63
Hoover Institution Archives
38 manuscript boxes (15.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, financial documents, catalogs, other printed matter, and photographs relating to libertarianism and publishing in the United States.
Laissez Faire Books.
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
1972 Laissez Faire Books opens in New York City, founded by John Muller and Sharon Presley.
1982 Andrea and Howard Rich buy Laissez Faire Books.
1989 Laissez Faire Books moves to San Francisco, California.
1993-1995 Laissez Faire Books reaches peak revenue of $1.3 million per year.
2002 Laissez Faire Books goes bankrupt and is sold to the Foundation for Economic Education.
2003 Laissez Faire Books is sold back to Andrea and Howard Rich. Andrea Rich gives Kathleen Nelson Laissez Faire Books, and it is relocated to Little Rock, Arkansas.
2008 Laissez Faire Books announces it is going out of business. Laissez Faire Books is sold to the International Society for Individual Liberty.
2011 Laissez Faire Books is sold to Agora Financial LLC, and is currently still operating under this company.
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection contains correspondence, financial records, serial issues, photographs, and other printed matter relating to libertarianism and book publishing in the United States.
Libertarianism--United States.; Publishers and publishing--United States.
- Correspondence, 1972-2002
  - General, 1982-2002
    - A, 1984-2002 (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - B, 1982-1996 (Box-folder 1: 2-4)
    - C, 1984-1996 (Box-folder 1: 5-6)
    - D, 1986-1996 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - E, 1985-1994 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - F, 1982-1997 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - G, 1982-1998 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - H, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 2: 4-5)
    - I-J, 1984-2002 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - K, 1985-1999 (Box-folder 2: 7-8)
    - L, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
    - M, 1982-1996 (Box-folder 3: 3-4)
    - N-O, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - P, 1983-1997 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Q-R, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - R, 1984-1994 (Box-folder 4: 2)
    - S, 1983-1996 (Box-folder 4: 3-4)
    - T, 1983-1995 (Box-folder 4: 5)
    - U-V, 1983-1994 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - W, 1983-1998 (Box-folder 4: 7)
    - X-Z, 1984-1996 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Individuals, 1983-2001
    - Branden, Nathaniel, 1984-1993 (Box-folder 5: 2-3)
    - Hazlitt, Henry, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5: 4)
    - Hess, Karl, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Hessen, Robert, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 5: 6)
    - Kephart, Bob, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
    - Palo Alto Book Service, 1984-1986 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Petersen, Dyanne, 1994-2001
      - 1994 (Box-folder 6: 2)
      - 1995 (Box-folder 6: 3)
      - 1996 (Box-folder 6: 4)
      - 1997 (Box-folder 6: 5-6)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 6: 7, 7: 1)
      - 1999 (Box-folder 7: 2-4)
      - 2000 (Box-folder 7: 5, 8: 1-2)
      - 2001 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - Telegrams, 1972 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- Multimedia File, 1958-1994
  - Discs, undated
    - "Mailing List,", undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - "Untitled,", undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - Floppy discs, 1994
    - "Roy A. Childs Reviews,", 1994 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Tape cassettes, 1958-1992
    - "Nathaniel Branden Parody (Rothbard),", 1958 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "Memorial Service for Roy A. Childs, Jr.,", 1992 (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "Klein Hayek Lecture,", undated (Box-folder 9: 2)
    - "Walter Block Supper Club,", 1986 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Photographs, undated (Box-folder 9: 3-6)
- Printed Matter, 1957-2008
  - Advertisements, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 10: 1-4)
  - Agendas and minutes, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - Articles and clippings, 1972-2008 (Box-folder 10: 6-7, 11: 1-5, 12: 1-5)
  - Artwork, 1992-1994 (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  - Book lists, 1993-1997 (Box-folder 13: 3)
  - Calendars, 1973-2002 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
  - Catalogs, 1973-2004
    - General, 1985-1996 (Box-folder 13: 6-7)
    - Laissez Faire Books, 1973-2004
      - 1973-1975 (Box-folder 14: 1)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 14: 2)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 14: 3)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 14: 4)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 14: 5)
      - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 14: 6)
      - 1985 (Box-folder 14: 7)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 15: 1)
      - 1987 (Box-folder 15: 2)
      - 1988 (Box-folder 15: 3)
      - 1989 (Box-folder 15: 4)
      - 1990 (Box-folder 15: 5)
      - 1991 (Box-folder 16: 1)
      - 1992 (Box-folder 16: 2)
      - 1993 (Box-folder 16: 3)
      - 1994 (Box-folder 16: 4)
      - 1995 (Box-folder 16: 5)
      - 1996 (Box-folder 17: 1)
      - 1997 (Box-folder 17: 2)
      - 1998 (Box-folder 17: 3)
      - 1999 (Box-folder 17: 4)
      - 2000 (Box-folder 18: 1)
      - 2001 (Box-folder 18: 2)
      - 2002 (Box-folder 18: 3)
      - 2003 (Box-folder 18: 4)
      - 2004 (Box-folder 18: 5)
  - Contact information, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 19: 1-2)
  - Contracts and proposals, 1990-1992 (Box-folder 19: 3)
  - Emails, 1994-2003 (Box-folder 19: 4-8)
  - Faxes, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 19: 9, 20: 1-4)
  - Financial documents, 1982-2005
    - 1982-1987 (Box-folder 20: 5)
    - 1982-1998 (Box-folder 20: 6, 21: 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box-folder 21: 2)
    - 1990 (Box-folder 21: 3)
    - 1991 (Box-folder 21: 4)
    - 1992 (Box-folder 21: 5)
    - 1993 (Box-folder 21: 6)
    - 1994 (Box-folder 21: 7)
    - 1995 (Box-folder 22: 1)
    - 1996 (Box-folder 22: 2)
    - 1997 (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - 1998 (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - 1999 (Box-folder 22: 5)
    - 2000 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - 2001 (Box-folder 23: 2-3)
    - 2003-2005 (Box-folder 23: 4)
    - Accounting books, 1977-1982
      - 1977-1982 (Box 23)
      - Undated (Box 24)
  - Flyers, 1983-1988 (Box-folder 23: 5)
  - Manuscripts, 1962-1997 (Box-folder 24: 1-4, 25: 1-7)
  - Memoranda, 1980-2002 (Box-folder 26: 1-7, 27: 1-6, 28: 1-3)
  - Miscellany, circa 1994 (Box-folder 28: 4)
    Scope and Contents note
    Contains miscellaneous printed matter such as a CD catalogue for Roy A. Childs's memorial service, a customer survey, postcard templates, and job listings.
  - Order forms, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 28: 5)
  - Pamphlets, 1973-1999 (Box-folder 28: 6-7, 29: 1-2)
  - Press releases, circa 2003 (Box-folder 29: 3)
  - Reports, 1957-2002 (Box-folder 29: 4)
  - Serial issues, 1972-1993
    - Ayn Rand Periodicals, 1987 (Box-folder 29: 5)
    - Books for Libertarians, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 29: 6)
    - Critical Review, undated (Box-folder 29: 7)
    - Laissez Faire Review, 1973-1985 (Box-folder 29: 8, 30: 1)
    - Libertarian Review, 1974-1981
      - 1974-1975 (Box-folder 30: 2)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 30: 3-4)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 30: 5)
      - 1977-1978 (Box-folder 30: 6)
      - 1978 (Box-folder 30: 7)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 31: 1)
      - 1979-1980 (Box-folder 31: 2)
      - 1980 (Box-folder 31: 3-4)
      - 1981 (Box-folder 31: 5, 32: 1-3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1984-1992 (Box-folder 32: 4)
    - Outlook, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 32: 5)
    - The Objectivist, 1962-1969 (Box-folder 32: 6, 33: 1-3)
    - Rothbard-Rockwell Report, 1992-1993 (Box-folder 33: 4)
- Speeches and Writings, 1980-1999
  - Notes, 1980-1999 (Box-folder 34: 1-4)
- Subject File, 1972-2002
  - Ayn Rand, 1982-1999 (Box-folder 34: 5-6)
    Contains issues of the Laissez Faire Books catalog, newspaper articles, lists, notes, and other printed matter relating to the objectivist author Ayn Rand.
  - Critical Review, 1988-1989 (Box-folder 35: 1)
    Contains correspondence, stationery, financial documents, and other printed matter relating to the magazine Critical Review, a project involving Laissez Faire co-owner Howard Rich.
  - Eastern European outreach, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 35: 2)
    Contains photographs, correspondence, essays, and other printed matter relating to Laissez Faire Book's outreach into Eastern European countries, such as Czechoslovakia, Ukraine, Poland, Hungary, and Romania, post-communism as an attempt to promote libertarianism. They established an outpost of Laissez Faire Books in Bucharest.
  - Events, 1972-1991 (Box-folder 35: 3-5)
    Contains invitations, guest lists, pamphlets, photographs, and other printed matter relating to social and fundraising events held or attended by Laissez Faire Books.
  - Feminism, 1991-1994 (Box-folder 35: 6)
    Contains pamphlets, newsletters, profiles, and other printed matter relating to feminism and the Association of Libertarian Feminists.
  - Hillsdale College, 1996 (Box-folder 35: 7)
    Contains speeches, notes, correspondence, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to a talk Laissez Faire co-owner Andrea Rich gave at Hillsdale College in Hillsdale, Michigan.
  - Laissez Faire Book Club, undated (Box-folder 35: 8)
    Contains several flyers about the Laissez Faire Book Club, a positive selection mailing list that allowed members to pick and choose their monthly book mailing.
  - Laissez Faire Books website, 1999-2001 (Box-folder 36: 1-4)
    Contains correspondence, artwork, notes, and other printed matter relating to the development of the Laissez Faire Books website.
  - Libertarian institutes, 1982-1993 (Box-folder 36: 5-6)
    Contains newsletters, pamphlets, and other printed matter from various libertarian institutes, such as the Cato Institute, the John Locke Society, and Libertarians Futurist Society.
  - Nathaniel Branden, undated (Box-folder 36: 7)
    Contains newsletters, articles, and other printed matter relating to Nathaniel Branden, former lover of Ayn Rand.
  - Palo Alto Books Service, undated (Box-folder 37: 1)
    Contains mailings, catalogs, and other printed matter relating to Palo Alto Book Service, a distributor of books that was based in Palo Alto, California.
  - Thomas Szasz Award, 1996-2002 (Box-folder 37: 2-5, Box-folder 38)
    Contains correspondence, guest lists, pamphlets, nomination packets, and other printed matter relating to the Thomas Szasz Award for Outstanding Contributions to the Cause for Civil Liberties.